Hello everyone and welcome
to EnglishPod, my name is Marco.
My name is Catherine and today we're
talking about someone who's very very dirty.
That's right and
actually not only are we
talking about something being dirty,
but also that we want to clean everything.
Okay, so you'll learn how to call someone
who likes clean things in English today.
Let's take a listen to our dialogue.
Ah, this bathroom is a pig's die.
Helen, why do you keep splashing a toilet?
What's wrong?
I just can't stand it.
It's really gross in here.
There's a stain on
the toilet seat and the
floor was wet and
slippery, so I cleaned it.
You did what?
Helen, I know it's gross, but I've seen
many public washrooms that are much worse.
Why are you cleaning the countertop?
Are you out of your mind?
I can't help myself, it's
just so disgusting in here.
Helen, this is not like your own bathroom,
just leave it to the cleaners, okay?
Hang on.
I'm just going to quickly
wipe this sink into the floor.
You'll suck a neat freak.
I'm out there.
All right, we're back
so this girl was very
much of a neat freak
and we're going to take
a look at that word
a little bit later on.
Why don't we go back
to the very beginning and
take a look at some vocab
on language takeaway?
Language takeaway.
The first word we have here on
language takeaway today is pig-stuy.
This bathroom is a pig-stuy.
Okay, so pig-stuy is a
place where pigs live.
Okay, so now this
obviously the bathroom is
not really a place
where pigs live, so if you
call something a
pig-stuy, you're saying that
it's very dirty, you're
saying it's disgusting,
it's very, very dirty,
like a pig-stuy.
So actually if you go
to a farm and you see
where all the pigs are, that
is actually called a pig-stuy.
Right, there's mud and
dirt, yeah, that's a pig-stuy.
So someone who is very, very
dirty, you can also call a pig.
Okay, now she was saying that the bathroom
is so dirty and it's really gross in here.
Okay, so gross means
something is, she doesn't like
it, it's really dirty and
makes her uncomfortable.
So something that doesn't
taste good, you can say it's gross.
That's right, so I don't like to eat
snake, I think eating snake is gross.
Okay, very good, so something that is gross
is something that's not really nice, maybe
a taste bad or it smells bad,
something that is bad in general.
That's right.
Okay, so she went
on to talk about the
toilet seat and that there
was a stain on the toilet seat.
Okay, a stain is usually a bad thing, it
means that there's a color or a mark that's
permanent or maybe can be
washed away on something.
So in this case, the toilet seat has a
mark on it, maybe it's brown or yellow.
But I can also say I
was drinking wine and I
spilled the wine on my
shirt and it left a stain.
Right.
There's always this red part on
my shirt, it can't, it won't go away.
Okay, so a stain is a mark
that usually won't go away.
Okay, so then she went on to describe
the bathroom as being disgusting.
So I guess it's very similar to gross.
That's right, something that is
gross is usually also disgusting.
I can say, "Ugh, this food
is awful, it's just disgusting.
" Okay.
But I can also say in this case, "Ugh, your
room is disgusting, you need to clean it.
So dirty or bad or unappealing.
" So something that is gross, something
that is disgusting, is something negative.
Yes.
Okay.
And then we have our
keyword and the title
of this lesson for
today, "They Need Freak.
" Her friend says,
"You're such a neat freak.
" That's right, so a neat freak is someone
who likes things to be very clean, okay?
And so a neat freak
does not live in a pig's dye.
Right.
It does not like to be
in pig's dyes, a neat
freak likes things to be in
order and organized and clean.
So maybe somebody
that's cleaning all the time
or that's very, very organized, you
can say that that person is a neat freak.
He is a neat freak or she is a neat freak.
Now, it's not necessarily
a good thing to be
a neat freak, but it's not terrible
either to call somebody a neat freak.
You can say, "Hey,
are you a neat freak?
" Right.
I mean, are you really
concerned about cleanliness?
Uh-huh.
Okay.
Very good.
So a lot of great vocab.
Why don't we take a look again at
our dialogue and we'll be back in a bit.
Why are you cleaning the countertop?
Are you out of your mind?
I can't help myself.
It's just so disgusting in here.
And this is not like your own bathroom.
Just leave it to the cleaners, okay?
Hang on.
I'm just going to quickly
wipe this sink and see the floor.
You'll suck a neat freak.
I'm out there.
Okay.
All right.
We're back.
So now let's take a
look at fluency builder.
So the first thing we want to talk about
today is this phrase, "I can't stand it.
" So this is our
neat freak talking.
She says, "I just
can't stand it.
" I just can't stand it.
So if you can't stand something,
that means that you can't tolerate it.
That's right.
It means, "I don't like it.
I don't want it anymore.
I need to change it.
" Mm.
Okay.
So, for example, if a bar is too
loud, you say, "I have to leave.
" "I can't stand it.
" It's too loud in there.
That's right.
Or if you are next to me all day and you
do, tap, tap, tap, tap, tap with your pen.
I say, "Marko, stop it.
" I can't stand it anymore.
Okay.
Very good.
And then she went on
to explain or to justify
why she was cleaning
the public restroom.
And she said, "I
can't help myself.
" It's just too
disgusting in here.
I can't help myself.
So this means that I
cannot control my actions.
Mm-hmm.
I can't control what I do.
And so, in some cases,
with a neat freak, the
person really needs
everything to be clean.
And so she says, "I can't help myself.
I have to clean.
" Okay.
So, it's a phrase like this.
Don't try to separate it and try to
define what help and help yourself.
It's more of a phrase
saying, "I can't control myself.
I can't control my actions.
I can't help myself.
" Or in the case of another person,
you say, "She can't help herself.
" He can't help himself.
Right.
So maybe you'd like to
smoke and you're smoking
all the time and you
say, "Stop smoking.
" You say, "I can't help myself.
I have to smoke.
" Yeah, I have to smoke.
Okay.
And for our last phrase,
she said, "Hang on.
" I'm just going to quickly wipe
the sink and sweep the floor.
Hang on.
This means, "Wait.
" Wait a moment?
Yeah.
So this is a really common
phrase we hear in English.
It's something that you'll hear all the
time in a pretty relaxed environment, not
maybe in school, but if someone says,
"Okay, I'm going to go see you later.
" And the other person
wants to say something to you.
You say, "Hang on.
" Hang on.
Wait a moment.
I have to tell you this thing.
So you wouldn't really use it
with your boss or a customer.
You wouldn't say,
"Hang on a second.
" No.
You would say that with a friend
or family member, things like that.
Okay.
So it's a very informal way
of saying, "Wait a moment.
Wait a minute.
" All right.
So the formal
way is, "Please wait.
" "Please wait.
" And the informal
way is, "Hang on.
" Hang on.
"Hang on a second.
" Mm-hmm.
Which is, "Hang on a second.
" All right.
That's all.
The words we have for today when
we review our dialogue one last time.
This bathroom is a pink stye.
Helen, why do you keep splashing a toilet?
What's wrong?
I just can't stand it.
It's really gross in here.
There's a stain on the toilet seat
and the floor with wet and slippery.
So I cleaned it.
You did what?
Helen, I know it's gross, but I've seen
many public washrooms that are much worse.
Why are you cleaning the countertop?
Are you out of your mind?
I can't help myself.
It's just so disgusting in here.
Helen, this is not like your own bathroom.
Just leave it to the cleaners, okay?
Hang on.
I'm just going to quickly wipe
this sink and sleep before it.
What's up?
A neat freak.
I'm out here.
Okay.
All right, so talking about
cleanliness and being a neat.
What type of person are you?
Do you usually, are you a neat freak, do
you keep everything very clean and ordered?
I'm not a neat freak, but
I'm also not a pig, not a slob.
I like things to be very organized.
Okay.
But I'm not really concerned
about cleaning so much.
Okay.
That's really easy.
So there's a difference for me.
In my house, I know
where everything is, but
maybe there's clothes on the floor and
there's books in the bathroom and yeah.
So I'm in the mill.
What about you?
Are you a neat freak?
No, I'm not really a
neat freak per se, but I do
like everything to be very
clean on the other hand.
So I can't really stand
it when things are, if
things are out of
order a little bit, that's
okay, but if things are
dirty, that really gets to me.
But I'm not the type
of person that has, you
know, folders with all
my bills in one folder
or labels or even when I was in school,
I didn't have my notebooks in order.
Really?
But yeah.
So we're the opposite.
Yeah.
Exactly.
But I hate things that are dirty.
Uh huh.
Interesting.
Well, let us know.
Are you a neat freak?
Our website is EnglishPod.com.
You can talk about yourself all
over that lesson comments area.
That's right.
Any other suggestions or
comments, we're always there as well.
And we'll see you guys next time.
Bye.